we're gonna go back to the lung room
okay we're gonna start because we've
been going kind of slow which is what
geshe-la does and there are six triggers
for kaliesha there are six chiggers four
negative thoughts and we did one of them
the other day and that's where you think
about you get in the presence of someone
who's causing you trouble okay so in
Tibetan that's called mikvah presence of
the object so the thing that you have an
addiction for someone's comes in the
room eating a doughnut and geshe-la
desire glacier starts to get strong or
someone comes in the room especially if
you didn't expect them and you had
trouble with them in the past and the
presence of the object whether it's a
donut or someone you had a fight with
before it starts to put you off balance
right and those of you who studied ACI
sorry DCI level 10 this is the
preliminary to getting upset and getting
upset is the preliminary to anger and
anger is the preliminary for resentment
you know holding it for weeks or months
or years there's a big joke a nun I went
to a talk by a Buddhist nun and she said
something cause she said uh you know the
ex-boyfriend who called you stupid he
forgot about it the next day but you
still remember 20 years later you still
hold it you still remember these fights
you had with people so the first trick
there's six triggers for clay sure there
are six triggers and we're going through
them
mon-monday very slow first trigger the
person yeah the object the person or the
donut comes in the room okay and then
the breath starts to speed
the heart starts to speed up and the
morning Diamond Mountain peaceful mind
water starts to get choppy okay and so
those are preliminary to getting so it
goes like that off balance
first you get off balance then you get
upset upset you still didn't say
anything yet angry you say something and
then resentment you hold it for weeks or
months okay after that there's four
steps to Glacier okay most glaciers so
what we learned the other day is one
approach for beginners lower school
because it doesn't work on the here just
works sometimes try to avoid the person
or try to avoid donors you know ask your
friends not to bring Donuts in the room
okay and it's not a very good method but
it's better than nothing and find out
the address of your ex-husband and
ex-wife and never go to that city make
sure you follow their travel plans and
never meet them you know okay and it's
not easy right and it doesn't work very
well karma will bring them to you
somehow or they're your friend we'll
start talking about them and your heart
beats speed speeds up and your breath
pizza okay so that's called object
factor one of the six triggers for
achalasia
okay second trigger we had today is bad
france we call dick jokes a big joke say
judo dicto judo Dopey's friend okay
dick means bad bad karma friend and then
cheedo
means a good karma friend
generally cheedo if you hang out with
them I was thinking about Rob Russ
injure I don't think he's here so I can
talk about him he's so nice and he's so
steady and he's so humble and he's so
sweet and he works so hard for all of us
he does all the accounting for a couple
of projects and perfectly and so when
you're around him your water stays calm
right called Chi dog dumb ofin and then
big dog means that I don't know you
around someone who's nervous or gets
irritated easily or says bad things to
people and then it infects you it
affects your behavior it speeds up your
heart normally speeds up your breath
okay so there's a tradition lower school
okay lower school try to not hang out
with those bad friends very often try to
hang out more with the Rob recen jurists
okay
and I don't know write a couple people
said bad friends not really a friend you
know like I had trouble thinking about a
friend who's bad because when a friend
is bad if you don't want to be a friend
but to be honest we all have bad friends
it seems like I don't know why we stay
around them but we do and so in the
Dharma in the Lum room
be careful with your choice of friends
and try to spend more hours with the
nice friends and then their habits their
behavior will rub off on you it will
infect you and try to reduce the time
you spend with people who are angry
people or jealous people okay because no
matter how hard you try they will affect
you they will affect you you will start
to act like them
okay that's the second one okay first
one object you know lower school avoid
that trigger you know
geshe-la should never go to Dunkin
Donuts at all or Tim Horton okay just I
should just avoid it forever and I try
you know not real hard but they have
this bad thing in the airport it's
called Cinnabon and I think they have a
fan and they send the smell of the
Cinnabon throughout the airport and it's
really hard to not smell it I guess
that's their plan
so the second thing is who do you
associate with okay who do you associate
with what was the third one is called
Lindsey said Dunsey Dinsey it's a good
word for a word to learn do you know it
Denton means too busy overstimulated
okay too much to do too much coffee too
many plans too many thoughts it's very
famous word it's called Dinsey and
ownership you do owns a jacuzzi okay and
it just means a breeding ground for
clashes is a busy mind okay if and they
and the internet is like 99% Dinsey okay
and it's it's unfortunate I mean it's a
good karma in our life like it's
revolutionizing Dharma teaching right
you can or yoga you can get a hundred
classes on YouTube thousand classes on
YouTube for free and that's wonderful
that's a great thing but uh but it also
keeps your mind really busy and
scattered maybe dungey is scattered mine
in english it means you're just thinking
about too many things and that's a good
place
just like to grow there it's like
fertilizer foreclosures okay if you get
too busy
your heartbeat speeds up your breath
speeds up you feel like you're running a
race right you're and that's a good
place for glaciers to grow okay so we've
covered three triggers okay the object
comes in the room you have friends who
influence you and then your mind is too
scattered and then it's more likely that
you will get angry or you will have
jealousy or desire okay
so part of the idea of diamond mountain
is to temporarily right help you with
those three triggers you know you're in
a cabin your ex-wife probably won't come
then you're trying to be around good
people here you know people are not
going to come out here if they're not
nice people usually and then third one
is you know your cut down you're not so
busy right while you're here and unless
there's a teacher training or something
okay all right so we've discussed three
triggers now I'd like to go to the I'd
like to go to the alarm room and start
start reading more in long room watch
the three triggers okay this is lower
school it doesn't always work okay
we didn't get to higher school it's the
higher schoolers first trigger okay we
didn't get to it yet okay alright here
we go
[Music]
so you can look up HL space R is a Cho
space R is maybe oh now I got a better
one for you
Thu space sh t hu space Sh yeah good
okay and by the way we'll take a pee-pee
breaking about you want to say 20
minutes okay
20 minutes so just hold it or go if you
want if you need to go just go don't
worry about it okay
we won't stare at you too much okay okay
Kandra chunky Tori sock talking this is
that son in sages text which means a
weapon or a blade okay okay Sanjay
corner and contour means anger okay so
we're on the subject of anger which is
the second of the big six negative
emotions and Tori means your future life
to go up in your future life or to stay
a human if you want to destroy your
chances then get angry a lot okay Tok
means it steals your future human life
okay because it burns so many bad sees
okay I say saltar canto you know no
monkey no negative John J - word 50
bucks Patricia he cuz you'll never get
it he
close very close but no cigar
so tisha means most powerful most
powerful okay yeah it sure is
est in Tibetan those of you who are
learning to been SH OS is EST
superlative mostest of the mostest okay
so the Trisha means our most powerful
and the most powerful John J was the
jump J destroy your of your good karma
is anger
Endora pinche it shows you into the
lower realms why you burn your good seas
and just your bad seas are the only
thing left okay
so what's so for zero dollars you owe me
$100 if you don't know it principal okay
we like principal puffs okay Lum gets
all right lumps on lump sum so it's all
means not therefore ye BAE can check big
problem in your life very big problem
now I'm gonna read the first line again
okay tell me something about it ready
Kandra turn the tories so torching it's
poetry okay which means it came from
somebody else he's quoting somebody so
in our translation team we require that
the translator goes and finds it because
we have a database so it doesn't take
that long it takes a few minutes okay
and then we require the translator to go
read the rest of the verse okay
it's only a single line okay so if
you're interested which you should be
this comes from a verse by it tsongkhapa
about Amitabha about how to go to a
meter bus heaven okay sukhavati having a
bliss okay so this is a from a famous
poem about how to meet Amitabha okay
[Music]
okay
and we actually covered that verse okay
here we go again
Lulla you tanky keeper yeah get that job
look now how does anger destroy your
good seeds get some means what word do
you remember yeah your bank account your
bank account your good deeds bank
account okay it's a special word in
Tibetan very important word in Buddhism
it's called virtual root but it means
you a good comment bank account okay
Joan look how is it that anger destroys
your good karma bank account Steven
asked me that the other day kappa dankey
kappa tell us epic ensemble tango then
can mean the angry and the anger okay
who's getting angry and who are they're
getting angry at and the scriptures have
a long description of you know but it's
first level bodhisattva gets mad at
second level by yourself a second level
boy sama gets mad at first low boy
supper first of all boy saw gets mad
first of all by sir are you buddy
suffolk this matter are you buddy suffer
okay and there's a whole list and he
says here oak to chin took cup Nick
Young Jae I'll cover that later when we
covered their six perfections later okay
we didn't get there yet so it's an
interesting subject you know of course
you destroy much more seeds if you get
angry at a buddy suffer and
unfortunately you ready for this the
more Buddhism you know the more bad
karma you make when you get angry okay
ignorance is bliss
all right so if you understand seeds and
you still get angry you make more
Betsey's okay it's very sad okay it
makes sense though right you should know
better
so of course you should only you should
be careful you can get angry at non
Bodhisattvas but be careful not to get
angry at a bodhisattva okay
which is just a simple thing you have to
judge all the people around you and
decide who's a bodhisattva and who's not
and it's very simple thing right the
nice people are Buddhist tapas the
people who challenge you are definitely
not right Bodhisattvas or could not be
Buddhists and so you're safer to get
angry at bad people and don't get angry
at good people right we all know you
know your ex-wife could have been a
Buddha trying to increase your patient's
ability there's a precedent what's the
famous story early teacher in Tibet
come on yeah a tee shot yeah he had
hundreds he had thousands of students in
India he went to teach into bed for 12
years there was no flight home in fact a
war broke out in Nepal he couldn't get
home he was stuck in Tibet which they
say is a good karma of the Tibetan
people this war but out of thousands of
students as his attendant as his close
attendant he brought the most irritating
person he could find and the Tibetans
asked him you know you have is this what
Indian students are like is he a tip is
he the best you could bring because they
were a little bit disappointed because
you know they're trying to learn
Buddhism and they're kind of suspicious
you know if this guy is that is the main
student of
the great master and he's so irritating
then what's the other students look like
you know and auntie shed said don't
worry you know I I picked the most
irritating one to go with me and then he
makes me stronger
okay he makes me stronger so don't
knowing that anger at the Bodhisattva
burns a lot of bad scenes we have to be
careful not to get angry at someone who
might help us a lot which is next one
okay or ex-boyfriend okay all right why
do I always pick ex-wife ex-boyfriend
you love them the most and then you hate
them the most they go to extremes okay
we're gonna study extreme views later de
la super combo so yeah but then good so
be careful we don't know who's a heavy
climbing object okay that's a problem
okay to lock oh here's a I love this
line jing-mei told me be careful I was
telling her about it and she said be
careful when you teach it gets not you
might get in trouble but I don't care
I'm just translating get to LA control
me cheaper pants I'm Coney boom thing as
far as your students okay you're all
trying to do a site teacher right
he said never get angry at your students
okay but Pence and Connie don't beg chip
a double room room means but it's okay
to hit them with with your rosary things
you know oh but you want to help them
tough love top we call tough love in
English okay so he says I'm not talking
about hitting your students with the
Rosary that's fine as long as you want
to help them and you're not angry okay
and this applies to parents also there's
times when you're a pet I mean I there
was a student here who had a child
and two students actually and they their
children got hit by cars and killed
instantly
two students here and just step out on
the street and give so to spank them
when they step out on the street you
know to shake them that's a good thing
okay that's a good karma okay got it
tough love it's better than dying right
okay all right
I'm happy to say we reached the third
depressing emotion we had desire we had
anger and now we do not yell not gay
which means I'm King which means pride
okay so now we go on a study of pride
I'm sorry this section is kind of
depressing we are studying the dirt in
our own mind okay but the ideas you can
get rid of it okay by the way nine more
minutes okay just hold that peaceful
water okay Ron nickytom Jorian Terry
Roush it up so Jim sang some was soaked
on he starts to list the things that
people get prouder top means Tom Joe
means authority power okay young 10
means I know Tibetan I can translate
Chinese Tibetan sounds good I can give a
lecture about it in perfect English
regrew I come from - I'm a good family
or I come from Germany like a very
successful country we are all cool
people green people you know so like
national or family pride okay we grew
up I understand emptiness better
than you you know like I can read some
GABA you know I I had an emptiness
experience you know
I'm I'm superior okay Tim Tama I keep my
six times book better than you do which
is not true engage you last case but I'm
I'm just saying as an example okay so uh
you know I'm more moral than you are
okay and so this is interesting we're
talking about qualities that you
actually do have so you do have good
study you do have good meditation you do
have good morality but you get proud
about it you start to compare yourself
on other people it's the best way to
have a miserable yoga class also right
there's always something the class going
to do something better than you it's
totally irritating so sooner or later
you have to give it up okay just I used
to not go to class because I didn't want
to look like the worst one in the class
and then I got to be the second worst
one the class and it was okay I can go
because I can look at the worst one and
say I'm better than you
okay time I kiss someone so what's the
idiom what's the next item what's
happening in the next picture in your
meditation book look at your meditation
board
what's the next item I'll give you a
clue it's number five huh what's going
on the lady's taking a shower listen
she's singing in the shower okay that's
where I always sing I don't know why it
always sounds better I mean according to
Veronica it doesn't sound better but it
sounds better to me I don't know so
people go in the shower and they sing
and then Donna do you know word turner
it means that even with such a small
thing as how you sing in the shower you
will compare yourself to others showers
singers you know I sing better in the
shower and then Veronica sings and you
know like you will get pride about
little tiny
things you know my ear curb is better
than your ear curve you know anyway I
was gonna give some gross example okay
even China means even down to people get
proud about their voice you know this is
how they sing in the monastery a good
voices is an important thing you know I
have a better voice than you do and
people get very it's a very big thing
you know people get very attached to how
they chant you know during the chanting
of prayers about not having clashes
they're having a closure about how they
chanted I understand I don't know we
would never do that
sung in Congo McNair same canvas same
came but means you full of yourself okay
I'm so cool what's that James Brown song
Stanley I'm so cool word kiss myself
[Music]
you got that video yet shopping you gave
it to them no let's show it today
something else tell me can be proud
about okay so the examples play now
remember Nate Donna I did promise you a
pee-pee break I got four more minutes if
you're looking down if you go to the top
of this mountain by the way this tall
mountain in the back which we named that
to the first director here that you
should thank him someday winston
McCullough he found this place and he
paid for it he put his name on the
contract and he offered to pay for it
like he he he offered to work for 30
years to pay for it and you know then we
said no but he he had the courage to to
sign for the place I was in to e retreat
he couldn't ask me I said fine a retreat
center I was kind of thinking San Diego
on the beach but okay anyway when I got
out the car drivers are you saying but
uh anyway we called that mountain after
him it's called McCullar peak okay so
five means you're up on the top of the
peak and everybody else looks lower okay
it's like you're up on McCulloh peak and
everybody else looks lower shimma shimma
shimma choked as in I'm number one Shemp
Oedipa Morrison everybody else is a
little bit less than me of course I'm a
cool person I'm not stupid
I don't tell people around me they're
all worse than me but I think it inside
my mind I think it but I'm out of there
I'm telling anybody you know you're just
a little bit worse than me or you're
really worse than me but uh quietly I'm
up on that mountain judging other people
around me okay and and people ask me
what's the Karma for people judging me
or people being unkind to me or people
writing things about me on the Internet
and I think it's judging people quietly
quietly judging people around us I'm
really good at it but I think this is I
think that karma is causing a lot of our
trouble for all of us okay okay
Tony member czev kupa so it feels like
you are superior it's a feeling that
you're superior to others okay and it's
quiet it's inside your mind okay people
send out two problems number one list
they think they're superior when they're
not but a lot of people have the
opposite problem they think they're in
Fame and they're really cool some we
just should just switch
everybody should switch okay one more
sentence can you make you get some
chicks only me go back a day
Kadam comas in the TTB lingo count only
shown go down okay
this is okay when we have winter here
all the grass turns brown
okay and in the summer it starts to get
warmer and the green starts to come from
the lower valleys up to the higher belly
so Tibet is a very or valleys and
mountains you know so they're very they
think about valleys and mountains alone
in fact there's a theory that all the
sects of Buddhism in Tibet came from the
geography that people couldn't we want
this Lama taught in this valley and this
Lama taught in this valley and then it
stayed for a thousand years and you know
so anyway
grass tends to grow from the lower
elevations and then it's best to the
higher elevations what's the point yeah
humble people get better qualities if
you keep yourself if you don't if you'd
fight with your pride we all have pride
okay everyone in this room has fun we
all have it but there's two choices one
is to just let it go okay and the other
is to fight with it when you fight with
it it's uncomfortable it's better to let
it go just be proud you know and your
life will be easier it's like all your
other bad habits right it's kind of easy
to just let them go then to fight
against them okay
unfortunately after you buy you get down
okay so we have to fire them it would be
more comfortable not to fire them just
leave them alone
guess I I have pride this law has plan
let's just leave it okay it's more
comfortable let me be proud you know but
it hurts you in most bad seats okay and
then later you have a lot of trouble
okay
so unfortunately you have to fight
you're mine okay
fighting the mind I think this is my
idea of meditation people ask me what's
meditation I said fight it's fighting
with your mind okay good now you can
fight with the bathroom and come back at
please come back at less than nine
o'clock okay it's a funny note okay
nine o'clock big break take some juice
green juice okay okay let's start again
we're gonna keep going on alarm room so
we don't finish in 50 years okay nakaoka
Ganguly and dengue gym and oops um but
are now yeah yep Allah and then Kang KEK
are so they didn't have balloons in
ancient Tibet but they had a thing
called a balloon which is a sheep
stomach that you fill it was the plastic
bag of Tibet and you could put butter in
it or some power and it will hold air if
you blow into it it will hold their
sheeps intestines or stuff like them so
he makes a joke here which is pretty
much Tibetan joke Tibet jokes are really
bad they're boring and strange but I
guess every country is different right
so they say if you've fill a balloon if
a balloon is full you can't add more air
and that means if you think if you
already think you're super cool you
won't learn anything new
okay the more pride you have the less
you can learn new things because you're
already like a balloon which is full and
you think your fault
so you
learning new things from other people
because when you learn something from
somebody you kind of have to be humble
okay let me choose some young Miguel
jumbo Europe Amy de la Paix me talk
llama can't teach a person for years but
if that person has pride it won't sink
in you know no matter how much you teach
people who have a lot of pride they
can't learn new things because they
think they know everything you know my
llama used to call me mister I know I
know because I used to say I know I know
he said no you don't know maybe I have
this problem Dana Dean yeah Bert come
Kyra be a learning name there's a famous
I forget which llama it was maybe it was
a teacher he started to think he was
pretty smart that he knew a lot of books
and he knew a lot of Dharma and then in
a dream some Buddha came to him and
showed him thousands of books that he
never even heard of and then when he
woke up he's like oh maybe I'm not so
smart so come Kyra be a means all the
countless categories of things in the
world okay
it comes in a CIA for what's a CI for
proof of future lives it comes there for
$100
okay good so when you say omniscient you
know mr. know-it-all
kun ken who knows all things this is a
Buddha who knows all things the emphasis
is not that he knows the name of every
bird or he knows where all the kinds of
rocks or because that's countless
there's in many planets they all have
different things right the main point of
omniscience ists they know what will
help living beings to be happy and
that's the main kind of mr. know-it-all
okay so here he says come get up be a
means what's it yeah 100 bucks I'm sorry
he's gonna loan me some money to pay it
off Rabia means countless details of the
universe you know
yeah Miran give me Shep I'm not done
someday so think about it sometimes all
the things you don't know outnumber all
the things you know okay you don't know
billions of things you don't know what
the people around you are thinking
reishi gronke chew on they come apart he
says take your own body from the tip of
your head to the bottom of your feet
there's like thousands of things going
on inside your own body you know you're
nobody okay there could be cancer we
have a friend one of my students her
cousin died yesterday two days ago she
was fine last week she was just normal
person and then she felt some kind of
uncomfortable she went to a doctor
doctor took a x-ray said you have cancer
everywhere in your body all over your
body and she died after a week just like
that you know and she didn't know what's
in under the skin her own skin you see
so when you think very proud I know a
lot of things look you don't even know
what's going on in your own body forget
you know other people you know don't
feel so proud that you you know a few
words of Tibetan or something you know
you actually don't know what's going on
half
gender here could be already you already
have a lot of cancer we don't know okay
okay Charlie nail okay yeah gee you're
ranking me Shep I should remember you
but none something think about it
nah girl choke choke for $50 word I'm a
famous choke that you had good I got you
this is the word break it imperative
break it
now tell me where you heard it for zero
dollars yeah
in the monastery when they teach you
tongue a which is how to know when the
Buddha didn't mean what he said the
famous example is when you have a
disciple who wash the dishes but they
always break them so when you hear them
washing the dishes and they you hear
them I'm throwing the dishes around you
say Caio does it shut down
it means could you just break a few more
dishes for me okay that's joke so this
is the imperative form of chart to break
okay okay could you just break a few
more dishes what's it mean good don't
break the dishes it's like telling
people there's two extra consciousnesses
number seven full of bad thoughts
because it doesn't understand number
eight which is where your husband really
is when he yells are you okay he got it
that's break the dishes it's not true
but he's trying to get people to think
about how the husband come from them
okay got it
sometimes the Buddhist said something
wasn't totally true to try to get that
student to think about it and then they
would understand something later it's
like hey could you break those dishes
okay alright nobody got that I'm happy
okay number four
okay we finished pride and we came to
Myrick Park which is yeah if you want to
lose a hundred dollars say ignorance
okay but we call it misunderstanding
okay
ignorance means you don't know
misunderstanding means you know wrongly
okay you misinterpret something so
that's what we're talking about okay
cheer Monica JEP otamatone romantic
sermon la tarde
generally speaking my rig okay Vidia
ignorance okay miss understanding
there's a negative on it
there's he says look there's a negative
on this world in Tibetan it's not
knowing okay
modrich in Sanskrit is not knowing our
Vidya okay and primitive a negative
initial a comes into English sometimes
as I ignorant
okay ignorance got it okay so motto told
my tongue rig Merrick did you see it do
you understand it we just put a gotcha
gotcha means negative put it put a knot
on understand okay that's all jarred a
stick it on there Merrick ba you can say
not understanding you can say Matawa not
seeing you can say me shape on not not
knowing you can say me sell WA not clear
to you yeah these are all this similar
okay now next picture in your meditation
book if you get bored in the afternoon
because I didn't give you enough
homeworks what's the next picture number
six
number six the other number six there
you go
okay so I told you in when I'm in
Arizona you have to learn to drive when
you're in high school you're 15 years
old they teach you to drive my
mathematics teacher had to teach me to
drive before school this is a system
they pay him a little bit extra so and
the local car company will give you a
new sports car to the school because
they're hoping the kids will buy one
when they get older so they learn to
drive in a new sports car and like a
Model X or something so it was really
fun it's the last time I drove a sports
car and anyway you have three kids and
one teacher the teacher sits next to the
driver so they can put their foot on the
brake and I remember those of you who
know Phoenix Glendale Avenue we went
down and this girl was driving and she
turned down the wrong way on the largest
Highway in Arizona Highway 17 so you
know people are coming 80 miles an hour
at us and we're going the wrong way on a
highway okay
this is misunderstanding okay it's not
ignorant okay it's wrong way it's not
okay it's not that you don't know the
way she wasn't stopping to ask
directions she turned the wrong way oh
boy that was exciting
what are you doing you know and I still
when I Drive to Diamond Mountain I have
to drive past that on that street and I
often think about it it was really
exciting
that teacher gone it was like in a movie
you know anyway I'm still here okay then
he gives an example burn victim but
Dabang knocked on my arm oompe capping
upon me
ha-ah for example if you close your eyes
meet somebody double-o if the room is so
dark it's as if you close your eyes and
you don't see what's in the room ok if
you walk into room and there's no
electricity it's as if your eyes are
closed Mito machine dude then all around
you is the fortress the for what kind of
truth noble yeah I saw and somebody came
out with a new book called the Four
Noble Truths I'm like you know still you
know pet peeve Marsha yeah put the title
of a book is wrong like principle path
anyway ple so anyway what what you don't
know what you don't see in the room when
you have this clay sure is number one
then she the four truths okay the four
noble truths right just kidding
Linda karma and its consequences by the
way the English word consequence is good
because it means the connotation in
English is unwanted result you know you
don't understand the consequences if you
do this okay so it's it's a nice word to
use karma and consequences rather than
karma and result okay
quench oh yeah the three jewels I don't
know why but in many countries spiritual
words become curse words and it's the
same in Tibetan so if you angry you can
say three jewels sun ball and it's like
saying geez so if you want to embarrass
yourself with quesillo turn see
it means our okay I'm sorry
it's kind of sad right you see a street
Jules and it's the way that say in
like if you hit your finger with a
hammer you go out Quinn Johnston I don't
know why okay
anyway there you go people remember
curse words before anything total McNair
ranking more and they look meat or you
don't understand the nature of things
okay meat or mom but I like copper atoms
of fire okay okay you think fires hot
okay
the day you stop thinking that fire is
hot you understand emptiness okay
hot just there's we did it China's
subpar
we did 21 synonyms for self-existent I
think yeah cocktail we did about 21 of
them I think something like that my
latest one is called in I n okay hop is
not in fire okay got it
entertaining is not in your bad friend
okay or your husband okay
when you understand that you understand
emptiness okay so he says it here
running home they look me to--in mom but
they ignorant is thinking that the
yelling is in the husband and not coming
from you okay Dean in your mom Tom Jake
it's our this is the tower of all
negative emotions they all come from
this all all negativities come from this
okay
misunderstanding the husband okay
Dayoung ejected our mariachi to shape a
loop turner
now he's gonna talk about two schools of
Buddhism what they think is Merrick bond
and they're a little bit different
okay here we go
some people say dicta my sorry
marek but some people say
misunderstanding is the view of
destruction okay view of destruction now
there's a technical term in Buddhism
okay say dicta dicta so you can have
misunderstanding about your husband okay
your husband yells at you and you think
it's coming from him okay that's
misunderstanding your husband but that's
not what starts the Wheel of Life that's
not number one in the Wheel of Life
what's number one in the Wheel of Life
you misunderstand yourself okay
you must understand yourself and the
first time you see emptiness directly it
will be the emptiness of hustle the
emptiness of Nicolle the emptiness of
mark okay it will be your own emptiness
okay so misunderstanding yourself who
you are what you are is the is the first
link of the Wheel of Life
technically it's jig done okay
misunderstanding yourself has a special
name in Buddhism it's a code name okay
someone has to teach it to you
it's called view of the perishable
assembly okay
it's weird jig chocolate our wrong idea
about the collection of things which
will be destroyed and that's the code
word and in Buddhist philosophy from
misunderstanding yourself okay so you
can call it misunderstanding yourself or
you can call it destruction view okay
for $100
except word two reasons why it's called
destruction view yeah you can destroy it
you can get rid of it okay you don't get
it
say again nice yeah she got it okay
fifty-fifty there Ronnie okay I'll say
it again okay it's called G da and this
is the root of the samsara okay
it's a certain kind of misunderstanding
okay and it's always misunderstanding
yourself okay
so you say just put your own name after
misunderstanding for Nords
misunderstanding nor okay why do they
call it destruction view to two reasons
number one if you work on it for a long
time you can destroy the view if you
work on it for a long time you can
destroy the view number two it is
viewing something which will fall apart
its viewing a human body human mind
which will fall apart which will
self-destruct in time okay
so those are the two reasons by the way
in this text today and in the next item
what is the next item is there a name
there
oh no sorry
comes later sorry it comes later let's
forget that okay he kind of likes to
emphasize emphasize is there a
connection between between the two let's
put it that way I would give you money
because it's worth more money but I'm
getting nervous about my finances are
those two kinds of destruction connected
I'll say it again okay some people say
it's called destruction view because
it's looking at something which is going
to self-destruct which is your body
mainly some people call it destruction
view because you can get rid of it you
can destroy it is there a connection
between that view and the mortality of
your body yeah exactly
that view causes the destruction of your
body okay misunderstanding you
is why you have to die misunderstanding
Michael is why Michael has to die if I
understood Michael I could plant more
seeds to keep my body going or change it
into diamond okay if I understood
Michael I don't have to die
I think it's called destruction view
because if you have it
you will die you will be in the wheel of
life that's why it's number one in the
wheel of life got it if you really
understand the pen you don't have to die
okay
this and this and pen are the same okay
coming from you okay you can change it
later okay yeah that's a good but thank
you okay here we go
so some people say in this list number
five right are we on number five for
sorry
number four is dicta specific kind of
misunderstanding misunderstanding hassle
misunderstanding Nicole okay not general
misunderstanding some people say miss
under the structures view is
misunderstanding
sorry in the list of six main clashes
number four it's just misunderstanding
yourself some people say that okay ready
some people say today the shape a look
Donna some people say no
misunderstanding and destruction view
are not exactly the same thing some
people say that Parana then they give an
example top a lot do lo nom do and this
happens at Diamond Mountain okay you're
supposed when you walk around at Diamond
Mountain you should be watching for
snakes okay
watch where you put your feet okay
they're coming out around now they sleep
in the cold weather when I was digging
sand in my three-year retreat
behind my fence I hit a snake like three
feet down they dig down and because it's
warmer and and they sleep for the winter
well I was like digging sent for my
toilet okay so anyway they come out
about this time and you have to watch
where you put your feet okay and it's
just a thing when you walk in the desert
you watch where you put your feet and
you don't step over rocks or wood where
you can't see what's on the other side
lots of people got nobody got bit here
one person got be here once here we're
very lucky so far but be careful okay
that's why we don't bring small children
here anyway at dusk when you're walking
around and somebody dropped a piece of
rope you might get scared and think it's
a snake okay so that's called parpola
Doolin yum they truly worth double
mistake a piece of rope for a snake okay
here's the example double dicta that's
misunderstanding yourself they get
targeted thank the member pub they the
cause of the misunderstanding is dusk
it's that there's not enough light okay
remember popped a dusk has fallen
tarpon near look misawa and the real
nature of this the Rope is not clear
okay toboni
Morita that's the second idea about what
is misunderstanding okay first opinion
big bad thought number four is
misunderstanding me okay second opinion
no it's all the misunderstanding things
in the world because it's dark the
darkness of your mind
okay the dusk okay there's a difference
between the two systems okay and it
would be nice to hear more about it but
he doesn't give us
look nom appellant our DARPA the first
system is chandrakirti okay
the misunderstanding means all when you
talk about misunderstanding as one of
the six main negative emotions you're
always talking about misunderstanding
yourself whose systems that chandrakirti
okay when you say it's just I'm sorry
and he says it's also the other QT
Dharma candy they both believe that's
that's the equation which is
misunderstanding okay but talk Micucci
believes it's the other one about the
snake about the the darkness on the
snake okay
it's somehow those two are different
somehow those two opinions are different
who's who's told me a Sangha who's kuchi
the two brothers okay so that means a
Sangha and Vassar bond do they like the
snake one and Chanticleer tea and
dharmic here too like the I don't
understand Stanley if you're standing
okay got it
somebody could write an essay about it
someday
it's a difficult it's a difficult
difference and he doesn't say anything
more about it okay and I'm not gonna say
more about it cuz I don't exactly
understand anything okay number five
okay number five by the way I don't know
if it's if it's me or you why did why
didn't he start out with
misunderstanding what why is it number
four I mean seems like it should have
been number one
say again it is how the list is
classically written but I don't know why
maybe the worst ones at the back I don't
know
okay number fine say Tetzel you guys are
sleepy I'll give you a break in I'll
break your head no I got permission in
the text give me give me like five more
minutes I'll give you a mini break okay
stretch break judge green stretch pin
okay
moppet that's only doubt okay we're on
doubt danchi court on land it's on a
magnet you are focusing on spiritual
truths such as danchi the four truths
pain cause of pain and the pain path to
pain path to the in the pain okay or
control somehow three jewels or lending
karma and its consequences and you say
to yourself yo Dom I'm not sure they
exist or not you know men I'm not sure
it's that way or not okay you know me
I'm a tomboy conscious on that at some
point of similar tell me kinky topic
even like get K especially not
understanding the three jewels it's a
huge sorry doubt about the three jewels
is a special obstacle to seeing
emptiness doubt about the three jewels
is a special obstacle to sing emptiness
$100 why damn you getting worse than
word he's worse he is worth but you're
all you're all so expensive now having
risked to give an answer I'm sure you're
gonna explain how the three jewels
relate to emptiness
yeah yeah thirty-three dollars each
yeah good the essence of Buddhist
emptiness especially the emptiness party
the emptiness body that we already have
okay then what about Dharma nice
beautiful okay Dharma is books Dharma is
teaching Dharma is online databases but
real Dharma is the direct perception
emptiness Sangha good yes
specifically its people is sorrentinos
directly is Sangha it's not people who
wear red robes okay or orange robes okay
okay so he got that hundred dollars can
I'm not sure I can make it to the end of
the week
Ted topic and key topic Illinois then I
put a picture in there of Maitreya okay
in the meditations okay my trail for a
hundred dollars why did I choose my
trail for this subject
really you should pay me there should be
a system okay come on don't get yeah
you're fishing you're fishing for money
honey the correct answer in my class is
like a needle at the bottom of the ocean
how do you say that jeonghwan de it's
not women's in mind it's a hundred
dollar question okay okay Hassan one
more try yeah okay Maitreya gave
specific advice about doubt
Maitreya gave specific advice about down
What did he say yeah put it on the Shelf
okay but it's too late Stanley okay now
Maitreya said there's good and there's
bad dog and in some copper lineage you
are encouraged to question the teacher
okay you're encouraged to ask questions
challenge the teacher is its own copper
system okay so if you're going to be an
ACI teacher don't get upset when people
question you even if it's not very
polite okay you're you're at some copper
lineage you're like yeah come on man
give it to me give it to me I love the
first day I met my mama first
conversation we ever had you know
I drove from Princeton I went to his
class I was late because there was a
snowstorm and I sat in the class and
then after I had made an appointment to
ask him to be my teacher you know to ask
him if I could study and I I go into his
room you know and the first thing he
said to me is hey did you see Muhammad
Ali beat that guy up last night on the
TV Muhammad Ali's a very famous boxer
did you see him beat that guy up last
night
what did you see my heartily beat up
that guy I like no I don't watch TV then
he's like oh he says it's so cool it's
called rope-a-dope rope-a-dope don't
mean stupid person okay don't means
stupid Rob means rope right so in the
boxing ring there's three ropes so
Muhammad Ali's the most famous boxer in
ever and when he got old he's too slow
and he's little fat so he had a special
system he just leaned back on the rope I
said come on hit me
and the guy goes oh don't any kind he's
like hit me some more
and then the guys like then he goes boom
it's gone rabid dog it means the guy
yeah you get it why am I talking about
that ACI teacher come on ask me tough
question don't ask me easy question give
me a tough question okay my trash that's
some copper system okay you should
encourage your student to ask you tough
questions okay don't run away and if you
don't know it don't fake it tell them
honestly I'll look it up for you I'll
check I'll let you know tomorrow okay so
in that so copper system it's not wrong
to say I don't accept this right now I
understand you taught it right party
you're asking me about something where
is party yeah
maybe this answer coming from the Buddha
he said Maitreya said that students who
doubt that teachers instruction are the
best ones okay Maitreya said done need
to give me those students don't give me
those students who said yes yes Lama
everything you say is true because the
next Lama to come tomorrow will say
something opposite and they will believe
it without any reason you see I mean so
in this tradition
doubt is a very powerful good karma and
not a cliche okay
what's this doubt well so anyway that's
the in him okay my trailer he said
skepticism is good questioning the mama
is good okay but lazy doubt lazy down
okay if the llama says the answer is in
the answers in the Lamia read it and
then you're too lazy and then you don't
read it or they give you a good answer
but you don't think about it that's a
bad karma that's a major collation okay
it's number five okay lazy down okay
lays it out I don't want to think about
it's too hard to think about it okay
that's a bad karma
okay got it good down guess I listen
carefully I went home I thought about it
I still don't understand it I can't
accept it yet then Maitreya said put it
on the shelf wait wait wait another
couple of weeks or something don't
accept it just because the teacher said
it who said don't believe everything I
say there's a debate whether he meant it
or not okay take a break take a break
okay go have some quick doubt okay we're
going to continue
[Music]
today I'm going to give you a lot of
lamb rim okay because we're just going
to keep going maybe the last half hour
we will do some lamb rim review from the
old lumber okay so let here we go
so we're talking about doubt but when
you make a list of the 6 worst negative
emotions for your friends I give you a
suggestion as a teacher get you might
want to get them in the habit of saying
bad dog bad dog
so there's a good bout and a bad dog
okay and I think you have to get used to
that there's also a bad pride in a good
pride and in the diamond way there's a
good pride where you try to imagine you
an angel
okay and that's also called pride the
same word but it's a good it's a good
thing it's a very good thing like I'm
Biagio Guinea you have a problem with
that okay okay here we go
they aren't Gallic Galla one bug in the
group so he's quoting the first tile
Emma and you saw his painting yesterday
with the mustache which I'm sure he
shaved off the next day because monks
aren't allowed to have mustard okay
condiment McCullar amusing nepeta
daniela smart but st. thomas all a good
way to patch and had some shots a
cheaper episode so you know Peter right
Peter
like when we did the llama Triple A and
we all clap our hands there's a spirits
on this land this land unfortunately had
some conflict here
there was native people here and then
the white people came and killed them
and sent them to jail and so there are
many spirits I think on this man and so
we always make offerings to them okay
people who died so he says doubt is like
the spirit of a dead person who comes to
bother you
doubt is like the spirit of a dead
person who comes to bother you they fly
through the sky of misunderstanding to
get to your house okay
they tried to kill your understanding
and your happiness and they they take
the life of your nirvana okay what's he
talking about spirit called out pat down
okay so that's how he described down it
kills your chances for the runner okay
okay shame but W I went to check it
which is our translation team rule so I
want to check it it's in Sumpter boo
words like hurt some turbo turbo means
minor works okay scattered works okay so
it's not a major book he just it's some
like letter he wrote or something okay
all right Lane Bella Pennsylvania and
hold on if you doubt the laws of karma
and its consequences
lento it will hurt your chances for a
higher Arriba
Nancy litotes Amna if you doubt the for
truth it will stop you from reaching
nirvana DL atomic Naruto okay so listen
how many main negative emotions yeah I'm
not talking abou Dahmer okay I'm talking
Loman okay six okay the first five are
called famine or Tamil no means they are
not opinions about reality there are not
opinions okay
there are not ways of viewing the world
okay we call Tower
and we used to try to come up with a
name for all our organizations together
because they're so different and
sometimes long ago we called them all
world view okay so they all have the
world view so when you talk about six
negative emotions the first five are our
nickname not viewpoints not viewpoints
yeah
Sadie's wondering about number four me
too
and then that the last one okay number
six is called viewpoints viewpoints
inside of viewpoints there's five so how
many negative emotions now big ones
ten if only it's ten okay five are not
viewpoints and find our viewpoints okay
and that's a classical division of the
sixth major negative emotions the last
one has five parts okay and it's called
viewpoints so now we're going to go to
five viewpoints okay five viewpoints and
sages question in his mind and my
question is isn't misunderstanding of
your point and there's a debate about it
okay so if you have that question you're
okay
that's okay you know into the background
they'll say five of you five are not
views but the fourth one is of you it'd
be something like that
okay I'm sorry about it maybe if you
hold Vasa bondo and a song a viewpoint
about number four it's not of you it's
just dark snakes okay so I mean maybe
you can debate from there I don't know
okay so here we go here's the fire sorry
five parts of number six right five
parts in number six here we go
number one destruction view destruction
view which supports the idea that number
four is not destruction view okay cuz
it's in number six also okay
destruction view what is destruction of
you looking at me personally and mine
yeah me and mine okay there's a bit of
song all through the day I mean I'm I'm
in my I'm in mine it's a nice song it's
kind of like that okay chick Donny G
pitcher Changi Pumbaa
now here's word if you're interested or
say gee translators this is where he
gives his opinion on the word
destruction this is his opinion on the
word destruction and he says Jeep a
church a Depot blood-soaked the pieces
of you are gonna fall apart your your
arms your legs your heart your stomach
they're all gonna fall apart
that's destruction okay Pumbaa talk the
your five heaps are gonna fall apart so
that's why we call it destruction view
because it's looking at something that's
gonna fall apart
okay so Lamech knee it looks at those
fall apart pieces McNay and it says na
da na na dun na and you can say dark
turn dark
killer as me as mine okay does the wife
and the kitchen have dicta yes or no
yeah the husband is mine it's part of
dicta you see what I mean that's also
part of her life it's part of her her
family this is my husband you see I mean
so if she misunderstands the husband
she's having dicta okay because it's her
mine it's her mind it's not her me but
it's her mine
okay got it not done i year holding me
or mine
okay mmm question yeah I mean you could
say all objects okay I'm sorry you could
go there it's kind of mean okay make me
now why did he sing not and night and
then he said doc and donkey for $50 CAD
you expensive kids no they both say
doctor I mean no I mean why did he
repeat na na and then dark dark no not
really
just dark is more common its Atman so
it's more commonly used in Buddhism for
the husband who's not coming from me for
the husband who's not coming from me so
he says me or mine meaning self or
selves okay he wants to say look it's
misunderstanding me it doesn't
understand me because the word self in
Buddhism is a loaded word
it's admin okay it means self nature
it means fire which is hot it means
husband's which decided to you and those
two don't exist okay cool man okay Dada
we should have normal chain now $300
she's words like green even word there's
a problem major problem in this sentence
give it to me there's a major problem in
this sentence give it to me for three
hundred dollars you have ten count to
ten ten nine eight
I'll do three Pattabhi Jois seven six
five four four four four four four
chotto chotto uh three two one now you
got you failed
huh you're close but no cigar
okay I saved my money I kind of cheated
I went kind of fast up in Oman Chen
translated up no mention good the
wisdom which is cliche the closure
wisdom okay
you should be objecting wait guys la
there's a mistake in the carving it says
pleasure wisdom what's the explanation
do you remember okay I'll tell you
sometimes the word pragya refers to
controlling the capacity of intellect
intellect
it doesn't mean wisdom about emptiness
the word pragya and mati in sanskrit
loader can mean intellect
the capacity to think and every living
creature has it okay every living
creature has mati so sometimes the
definition of ignorance is corrupted
wisdom corrupted wisdom cool it's a good
translation by the way okay wisdom which
went wrong logic which got messed up
okay
so that's in the definition of Jake Tong
you know the guy's thinking the guys
trying to figure it out he just figured
it out wrong okay but he still has a
wisdom he just has messed up with them
okay stupid wisdom okay okay so when you
see that in a scripture don't call it
glacier wisdom okay call it defective
intellect
it means intellect the capacity to think
okay it doesn't mean wisdom here okay
got it
don't translate it as wisdom when you
see it connected to pneumo it always
means corrupt intelligence corrupt
intelligence misunderstanding in
Buddhist psychology is intelligence
corrupted okay understand it's an
attempt to understand but it's corrupt
but it's still thinking it's still
trying to figure it out okay but it's
wrong so we have this word in Buddhist
scripture called corrupted intelligence
okay which is stupid okay you know
corrupted intelligent people okay you
should have no mobile chin thing now I
put the next item number eight what's
the what's a picture
what's a picture I think it's a lady
with their mother dying or something
right it's a lady with her mother dying
something like that and the point that I
want to make in the picture is if you
have destruction view it will kill you
if you have destruction view you will
die one of the goals of Buddhism is to
beat death one of the goals of Buddhism
give me give me a nice word for that
where's JB he's not here
kala dhanda what's Khalid under yeah
take a stick and take a baseball bat and
beat death to death okay what's the
color time so in yoga tradition death is
called time okay good but it also has
connotations that black okay black
Mahakala for example okay all right so
that picture is supposed to remind you
that misunderstanding yourself
is why you die and if you could stop it
you wouldn't have to die okay and that's
why we're here
that's what we're doing okay so so many
people write me you know I don't know
yesterday oh my my relative died can you
pray for them and you know I'm polite I
said okay I'll pray for them but I would
rather they came to the lung room and
didn't die you said I mean it's kind of
frustrating for me to teach Solarian for
10 years people don't come and then I
get the email to pray for their mother
you could have told her not to die you
know just come to why you bothered
anyway
you can write them okay tell me she
loves irritating another pet I guess I
have a lot of pet peeves I didn't know
it's so many okay paranoid ronghua cheng
it to me so pena Chippenham for example
if another person says all stanley you
get such a wonderful class yesterday or
they say you made this mistake in your
talk yesterday okay praise and when you
come criticize Nietzsche Pinar if
someone hurts you Nala dead touch Apache
che then we tend to say why is he
criticizing me you know all right what
did I do
cheese shaming IIIi didn't do anything
lo puso Ling Ling Washington and then it
comes deep in your heart when someone
criticizes you there's a very very
strong instinct reaction in your heart
that says I didn't do anything I don't
know why they're your enemy okay
it's called Ling lingua you say Ling
lingua it means it just--whoop it comes
up in your heart you can't stop it you
know well I I didn't do anything why are
you talking about me like that
Ling Ling char char jung-hwa means it
comes up in your heart
death order your pawns in birthday
especially with the husband okay in the
kitchen the anger comes up like that and
you hold on to it okay they and that's
his description of destruction view
okay someone criticizes you and it's
this thing that comes up in your heart
right away says I didn't do anything in
the kitchen in the two husbands in the
kitchen skit what is it what moment is
it I need anything I need he's just
walking he's tired yelling at me okay
it's that that's a sign you have
destruction view that I didn't do
anything
when your heart says I didn't do
anything you have destruction you know
that's a what he call a sign that you
have it okay he's saying that's a sign
that you have it he's blaming me I
didn't do anything
okay got it I didn't say anything he
started yelling at me that means you
must have destruction view that means
you must die if you keep thinking like
that you must die okay all right and I
think that's why it's called destruction
view I would call die viewers no okay
die view you know you're gonna have to
die if you keep thinking like that if
you keep thinking it's not my fault I
didn't do anything
you will die okay all right Jake Todd is
soaked Chuck who has Jake time how many
people have jinked on how many living
being subject on what about ants at
Diamond Mountain okay he's gonna answer
it Jake taught the subject open e and
Chandler yeah
everything from ants at Diamond Mountain
honor has chikna
they have destruction view dive you okay
every living creature from ants on up
have died view Boudreaux in our shot
toward Cigna if an ant is headed for
your foot and you take a piece of grass
and poke him on the nose okay damn I
thought not chick jam donut chick chick
gentle then as soon as you poke the ant
with the grass they start to think I
didn't do anything
you know what what's going on
something's gonna happen
yeah I'm do cockney and they get scared
come come in son they when they come
they bought they go into a bar okay
curl up Hewitt Archer
Sheila means dead Jim means they fake it
they pretend they're dead
okay and then the relationship name
means they're gonna wait for a while by
the way word that's a really difficult
word in philosophy scriptures reishi so
here's a good real-life example of it
after a bit okay after a while they will
cut so long they'll turn there they'll
turn around and go the other way okay
that means they have died view okay I
need anything and they run out of the
kitchen or they run away from your foot
okay even bugs have it okay dive dive
you I ain't do anything they stinking
grass on me okay
turd young what the GTA chip array
the reason the aunt runs away when you
poke him with the grass is that they
have died view okay he says that's proof
to have died view I didn't do anything
if they're bothering me you know they
run away okay alright that's the first
of the sixth of the five that's the
first of the five of the sixth am i okay
you okay you still with me your guys are
amazing
I I don't know why you're not fond of
him but maybe you could maybe you
learned that trick you know so god bless
I'm happy you know I sat in thousands of
hours of classes in the monastery we
were very very poor we were refugees in
the roofs all leaked and they're all
grass roof grass in sits like a hundred
degrees in there there's no classrooms
forget it you're in your teachers
bedroom he's sitting on the bed and
you're all crushed in this little
bedroom and the monsoon is dripping on
your head you probably went to myself
during a Monson and it's dripping on
your head you know and it's really hard
you're sweating and it's dripping on
your hand and you say when I become a
teacher I'm gonna make those students
suffer you know 25 years you know I'm
I'm just waiting for some people to come
and ask me to teach them so I can make
them suffer each is so cool okay that's
what I'm doing now I'm getting revenge
all right here we go okay Tata say Tata
extreme views extreme views okay when
you think about Tata I don't know
there's a baby girl she coming with
Jessie lotar I don't know if he's the
one I one of those guys I he asked me to
teach him to drive and we went on a
12-hour drive to the winter debates in
triple 12-hour drive it's probably 200
miles or so so I said okay you drive it
all I'll watch you know and it's a
little dangerous in India because
there's always rice fields on either
side and they have ditches
if you drive a little bit off the road
you brake your car so and I remember I
was playing rock and roll because guess
I was asleep and it was with Jessie
Lothar and him and the guy at me were
playing rock and roll you know I was
playing what's that lady's name Tracy
Chapman I was playing I said check this
out I put put it on I said he said Oh
Tracy Chapman I I know I said wait a
minute you're in the mall
very how do you know Tracy chat you know
he's like well you know there's a
special thing called guy is a guy a it's
a two three weeks in this summer after
the summer between and you're allowed to
have fun you're allowed to play rock and
roll and you're allowed to play games
for like two weeks or three weeks and
otherwise you're not allowed to play
radio or look at suddenly every single
house has a radio it's amazing
anyway so we're driving down the road
get lots of sleep in the back and I'm
trying to teach him how to drive you
know and I every time I tell it be
careful he goes so that's TARTA extreme
you can't run in the middle you know
always good why he had this had this
thing with his body
he'd go why and he never got over it he
couldn't drive like shopping I just King
you gotta learn to drive okay so tight
that means you fall off the road you go
to extremes okay now what are extremes
like with eating okay
would like with eating it's a good
example okay one extreme is to don't eat
enough you want to be look skinny you
want to fit in your dresses or your
tight jeans so you don't eat enough okay
that's one extreme and you feel sick you
feel weak and you you don't feel healthy
you're not eating enough you want to
look skinny so that's one extreme okay
what's the other extreme you eat
everything okay a chocolate donuts you
can't stop eating
okay these are called eating extremes
okay now what's a philosophy extreme
here we go Jake take counseling they
need talked enter suit then do so so Tom
one is to believe many kinds of
solidness about me oh gosh that's gonna
be teaching here next year and next year
and we will finish the alarm in ten
years fifteen years that's one extreme
okay it's not true
we don't know guess I will be here
tomorrow okay get lost very fragile
people human beings are very fragile we
break very easy you get cancer very easy
so so that's one extreme okay I will be
here next year I will be here next year
that's one extreme okay I'm pretty
healthy dark means I'll be here I'll
always be here care sook means look I'm
I'm pretty strong I'm pretty solid okay
turns to means look I'm pretty I don't
have any big health problems
III kind of feel like I'm gonna be here
next year that's one extreme okay to
think that you're a solid okay Dan drew
is the ultimate solid I'm so solid I
come from myself and not from seeds okay
that's the ultimate extreme I don't come
from seeds
okay I come from me okay what's the
opposite yeah yeah I don't exist I went
to a teaching
allama said I was empty he said I don't
exist therefore the Lama could take my
money cuz the money don't exist and I
don't exist man I mean see when you when
you take emptiness to this extreme Oh
emptiness means I can do what I want
emptiness means not
thing matters emptiness means I can have
tantric sex with other ladies in the
class okay this is extreme this is this
is this one okay I'm gonna be here next
year as this one nothing matters because
everything's empty is this one
okay got it both off the road both going
off the road got it
that's viewpoint number two okay huge
Apatow assaulted in a Totoro potala
humor wrong Chuck he can't ended thank
chairman Thomas oh you know
he says there's versions of this that
people have who don't study Buddhism and
there's versions of this that people
have who study Buddhism so everybody has
it to some extent they think they're
gonna be around next year
okay what's the lowest kind of ignorance
misunderstanding
what yeah but set in normal English yeah
I mean you know are you gonna be around
for a while its dime mount gonna be here
for a while you know how long I don't
know 10 years 20 years but yeah it's
gonna be around for a while are the
people in this room right now I'm gonna
be around for a while I mean - laughs no
one would be so inconsiderate as to died
during the class I mean everyone's gonna
be around for a while okay for a while
it's the first form of misunderstanding
world abhidharma
right it's the ahh be Dharma version of
emptiness never say for a while never
say for a while
yeah you're gonna be around for a while
look I'm sorry I'm not allowed to say
that okay I don't know I can't tell you
I don't know it's time amount gonna be
around for a while I don't know North
Korea guy push a button
diamonds gone at four at 11 okay gone
America's gone will America be around
for well that's at the Romans don't
that's what the British thought
but you know there's a long list okay
okay so sit down so everybody has it
whether they're Buddhist or not
Buddhists have special one because they
heard about emptiness and they
misunderstood emptiness okay got it
Buddhist have specially nasty extreme
views okay number let's do one more and
then we'll do something else because
you're so tired say tower chongxin tower
chongzhen this is easy all those wrong
opinions we just talked about I come
from myself my husband decided to yell
at me I didn't do anything everything's
empty so it doesn't matter what I do I
don't have to be moral or nothing's
empty so everything is real the next
viewpoint is your viewpoint about your
viewpoints got in the next viewpoint is
your viewpoint about your viewpoints
okay so do you have the viewpoint that
emptiness means nothing matters
therefore you can have sex with
everybody in the class okay that's one
viewpoint wrong viewpoint right then if
someone questions you and says you know
is that really correct is that a good
way to think you defend yourself you say
yeah yeah I studied Buddhism
everything's empty I'm on the Tantra
path you know so I can do these things
okay like that okay so now you got two
viewpoints first one nothing's real I
can do anything bad thing I want number
two that viewpoint is good because I
studied Buddhism I read about emptiness
okay you defend your
viewpoint you have a viewpoint about
your viewpoint got it
that's called tawa chongzhen my
viewpoints are best my viewpoints on
number one okay Jonathan Jake Todd on
lockdown the dog jacket on he lists all
of him calm down then I can at any time
with our humble and mainly tongue to the
mission of no Monty know here he says
again word for zero dollars should have
no Mon chain yeah defective intellect
defective thinking defective thinking
about viewpoints my viewpoints are best
okay if you got this one you're really
in trouble
let's do one more for fun because it's
kind of depressing nah now let's save it
for tomorrow
okay I'll depress you tomorrow stop here
okay I'm gonna go to the historical um
room you have a document I think I know
you brought it to class you got it
historical um room
item number 85
item number 85 what's going on we are
now reviewing the lahrman for the last
eight years
okay what's going on know what's going
on in the picture yeah it's yeah lunch
direct the fast path you bypass yoga and
you go directly to lunch by the way I
think words teaching yoga right he
teaches Dharma mature style I really
like it I encourage you to go it's a
sweet style
that's the Lama stand on his head with
no arms anyway there's three ways to
serve people the teachings there's three
ways to serve people the teachings it's
very famous okay and that's the next
topic that we covered like seven years
ago and I'm just giving you a review
okay and I'm gonna read from the lahrman
okay Dayoung in dookie wonky goddamn
Shambhala remember damn lava sation
power Lumumba da Matta and it depends on
the capacity of the student if the
student has big capacity if the student
is as a big spiritual capacity they can
become ashume power okay it means a
classicist
Shoom power means classics guess where I
took a CIA name okay Shambhala this is
the word classics Asian classics okay
classics means important spiritual
classics big books important books okay
so but Punk are saying as a Buddhist you
have three choices how you go out it you
can be assumed power you can be an Asian
class assist you can follow the Asian
classics
and that's what you guys are and that's
what I specialize in
okay or you can be alarmed by yeah it
means someone who follows love me okay
they don't want to hear all the details
about Chandra kirtan Dharma carotene
guna Papa they're not interested in the
gardener just teach me lahrman just I
don't care about those ancient books
they're too hard and I don't have time
I'm busy
just give me some lumber okay so this
week we're doing both okay
why we're trying to put extra tools in
your tool kit we're trying to put
because you will meet students who who
can be classicists and you will meet
students who just want lumber
yes sir is there something less than
lumber
yes the good news say dumb Lhakpa I'm
not funny this is an interesting kind of
student often times they want to serve
the llama they will follow the llama
around and they don't want to go to
class they don't go to class they cook
they clean they do airplane reservations
and it's enough for them that they spend
some personal time with the teacher and
the teacher says look you know there's
this thing called diamond where they
don't have a formal class they learn by
being around the teacher okay
it's called advise assist personal
advice assist they get personal
one-on-one sweet personal teaching from
the lama and sometimes it's very very
powerful
sometimes it's the highest kind of
teaching they're cooking
they are sweeping they're running
Diamond Mountain they don't even have
time to come to class but they end up
being around the lama a lot and the lama
gives them sweet private in
structions and they end up becoming
Buddha first Artesia had two students
his cook and his secretary and the cook
was jealous of the secretary because the
secretary got to be in our teachers room
all the time and the cook had to be in
the kitchen all the time
and Ottershaw could read everybody's
mind and he saw that the cook was
jealous of the secretary so one day he
called them into the his room and he
said let's have a spiritual realization
contest and he examined their spiritual
realization
guess who won that cook so these cooks
get dumb rock they get private little
teachings from the lama when they go to
serve dinner okay and the other students
don't get it so I would say that there
are times when that's the highest kind
of student okay generally shubao is
safer okay
learn the classics or maybe do both
right learn the classics and cook dinner
okay and by the way I don't support
people cooking and not listening to the
class
nowadays there's no reason why even if
we hold the DCI event in in Bali at the
beautiful beach in Bali you know then it
would be nice if we had the speaker for
the people who have to work in the
kitchen or the people have to sell the
books or things like that I think we
should try to do that we should always
try to there's no reason not to do it
now this which we're streaming to the
kitchen also right so when it works okay
we should try so those are your choices
you can go deep into the scriptures you
can do lamb rim or you can hang out near
your lama and get like Jigme got that
right and she's so
oh yeah hey I never hit you with a
rosary I mean there's still time all
right
sometimes it's quite hard to be close to
mama
they say karmically it's quite hard you
know not easy okay all right next item
next major point in the last eight years
you got that you got the image of it I
don't know it's called the Lions crack
okay this is at a monastery called
rodding and it's a famous monastery
because Artesia I used to hang out there
and his student drum to Jay who was a
lay person he never became a monk huh
business yeah he was actually a business
man he's probably the most famous non
monk
teacher in Tibet and this was their
monastery and there was a little
mountain there was a little mountain
behind the monastery called Lions crag
because it looks like a lion okay and
it's very similar to this mountain back
here and there's a famous story that so
coppa was having trouble to teach until
copper was having trouble to understand
and the mom room so he went to this
mountain maybe you can try it he went up
on the mountain and he made a prayer he
just he just stayed for hours two hours
and he said I need help
on the lam rim
I don't really understand all of it and
he went and he did a prayer on this
mountain at near Roger
behind Roger and suddenly he had this
vision of all the great Lamas of the
lahrman and they taught him lamb rim
directly like a tisha and Buddha and a
Sangha manjushri Maitreya the holders of
the lineages wisdom and they all taught
him and and then he he decided to write
the nerman Tim oh okay he wrote the
great lung room because of that okay he
got the blessing especially the last
part which is shamaton they pass the
pass honor when tsongkhapa asked for
help
he wrote a poem to ask for help and
that's called lamb choke go Jay opening
the highest opening the door to the
highest path and part of that long poem
is called yun densha goomar
which is what source of all my good the
source of all my good and and I
translated bonkers commentary to it it's
called preparing for Tantra so the the
prayer that tsongkhapa said to get more
help about the lamrim is that book is
the verses okay part part of it why are
we talking about that
it's a methane in the lamb rim that if
you
meet if you want to improve your
practice or your understanding just ask
in Christianity they say when they say
asking you should know what something
about the door knocking it wasn't Phil
what's a knocking thing yeah they won't
open the door if you don't knock so if
you want help if you're falling asleep
in class for example in your mind you
can ask all the lamas of the Lum room to
help you okay teach me that trick about
sitting up okay so this is a very
accepted method of learning Buddhism is
to ask for help in your head you know
tsongkhapa hey I need some help here
okay and they read your mind okay and
they will give you him okay
because that's how he got his
understanding okay in this picture okay
so that's a very famous larum teaching
did you have a question yeah what's the
cover to get to help I bet it's the
motivation of how you ask
you know like I'm having trouble staying
awake in my meditation will you help me
and you can imagine some compass saying
why why should I help you
what what am I gonna get out of it and
then you gotta say oh sushi okay
I'm gonna make the whole world happy oh
okay yeah I'll help you then okay it's
you gotta make deals okay yeah I'd say
that kind of your motivation you know
why do you don't want to fall asleep in
your meditation like I want to help
people
okay all right next item there are four
classical methods of delivering the
lahrman teachings there are four
classical methods
of delivering the lamrim teaching and
what you have here it was hard to find a
picture certain pictures are hard to
find on the Internet
this is a dissection class these are
real dead bodies and this is a medical
school and they're learning how to there
they're cutting open the bodies to find
out where stuff is my roommate in
college his girlfriend was a medical
illustrator she has to draw the the
veins or the muscles so all day long
they're peeling off skin
they're painting dead bodies you know
and he one day he's like just come out
of the room screaming you know I'm like
what's going on and he says it was just
creepy I said what's creepy says she
took my arm in bed and she's going like
this so dissection teaching is one of
the four ways of teaching the Lamia okay
so I'm gonna give you four options for
how to teach Lamia okay there's four
options how to teach Lamia and that
here's the name is on your reading okay
commentary or dissection or experience
or experiencing okay these are the four
classical methods of teaching the Lamia
okay then you have a choice and you can
apply it to your ACI teaching okay you
have a choice here are four classical
ways of teaching okay here we go number
one till I say teach about singing
junior shiyagare by geobella sarah you
go through every single word of the book
one by one you read every single word
and you explain every single word one by
one
guess which one you're getting that one
that's how I decided to teach this
Lahm rim and that's why it's going on
for 15-20 years okay and I don't mind I
enjoy it I hope you enjoy it
I feel like I want to take my time and
just relax and enjoy it I don't have a
goal you know I don't want to reach this
page or I want to tell stories and take
long breaks drink lots of green drinks
somebody from Kazakhstan gave me some
great sweets eat sweets you know yeah
okay so anyway first option explain it
word by word I call it commentary it's a
common word by word coming okay second
option same Marty Marty that's called
dissection teaching Mar means red it
means the red meat under the skin team
is a teaching okay and it's very famous
in the monster it's called surgery
teaching dissection teaching dead body
dissection teaching and there was a
custom in Tibet in ancient times the
medical system in Tibet the old one was
very advanced and they had dissection in
the Western countries dissection came
very late because it was believed that
your your body should be hold for you to
go to heaven after you die so it was
actually against the law to cut a body
and so it took a long time in the
Western countries to do dissection but
in tibet it was a long long time ago
they were taking apart bodies and
checking them out okay and so the idea
is that teacher doesn't do word by word
they go to the big ideas and then they
relate it to your personal life okay
they just like look here's a sweet point
I'm not going to teach you the whole
page but here's a sweet point it's like
items you can say in them
okay it's the same thing okay ma polka
Cheney they strip the skin open they
show the major organs and the major
arteries and seek each or shame each
apart without doing much detail they
give you the essence here's the heart
here's the lungs here's the stomach this
is the main parts of the body
okay got it just the essence that's if
you're in a rush okay it's kind of love
what we're doing in the evening we're
trying to cover the alarm in ten days
right
ten classes that's kind of a Marty
that's kind of a dissection okay major
organs which maybe we should call major
organ teaching okay number three is
interesting saying say hang on say MT
the Lama will tell stories about their
personal life to teach you about the
principles okay like I was in three
retreat I was thinking about bodhichitta
I was meditating here's what happened to
me and that's called an EMT okay so
obviously you can mix Styles right in
the same teaching you could mix some
neon tea in with pity okay you could
promise the students every single word
and tell stories most of the time okay
about your practice or or lamas you
meant okay things like that okay now the
last one is kind of cool and I think it
would be kind of cool if you wanted to
do it someday it takes a lot of time it
takes more time
so the lamrim means steps to the path to
Buddhahood means there's certain topics
you cover one by one you never go out of
water and you always cover all of them
the first one is how to find a teacher
the first one is called nominal turn how
to find a teacher nama tencel
so there's a way to teach the alarm room
where everyone in the room has to finish
it actually before you go to the next
one okay like you have to wait for the
last person to find their llama then you
can go to Lamia number two step number
two got it
I imagine it would be really slow you
know or if you're doing death meditation
you don't you don't go back to Singapore
until everyone in the room is crying you
say I mean got it I I heard I heard
somebody tried it once and basically
they ran out of time you know so this
kind of teaching would be you don't go
on to the next subject until all the
students are crying if there's one
student who's not crying you have to
wait
everybody has to wait so I guess if you
had a lot of students it could be a mess
okay all right if someone doesn't like
to cry okay so those are the four
classic ways of teaching Lamia and
that's item number 87 which ones in the
picture
yeah the dissection okay which is where
you go for the main points this is hard
this is long this is main main organs
okay main organ teaching commentary is
word by word experienced uh by whom yeah
by the llama and they're sharing their
experience with the animals and three or
retreat or something okay and then
experiencing very difficult you know you
wait by the way it's not uncommon to do
that kind of teaching with three or four
students you know and that's actually
what happened with Caleb J and some kapa
that day they met some copper took care
of J into a experiencing retreat
and that was pretty cool
just two of them and he taught him until
he experienced it and then he taught in
the next step that makes that okay cool
all right we still have no we don't have
one minute
hmm can I use that maybe I'm gonna stop
there but we just reach the second day
of the teaching with you okay that we I
think this teaching is 24 days or 21
days I don't remember but we just
finished reviewing the first day because
we did the last bunch of days already
okay so we're not it's not too bad we've
done 87 major ideas and we'll keep going
cool cool mom it's a question mark in
Chinese right so if you say Kumar Kumar
then you say ah cool cool listo yeah
ready
how do you say cool sheilo cheeto cheeto
cheeto mac
oh okay Tim you got you got a
cheeto announcements oh who is cheeto
[Music]
Jackie you undoing perky time near
doubling Sheen and egg
some years and made
no gone and seen the tip I'm going on my
yeah
yeah son I'm you share thoughts or she
said to me Taj smoke